Edward Otto Tabor Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Edward Otto Tabor Papers 1918-1948
MSS42200
Tabor, Edward Otto, 1885-1948
3,000 items
10 containers
4.0 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Lawyer. Correspondence, reports, speeches, notes, photographs, printed matter, and miscellaneous material reflecting Tabor's part in the activities of Czechoslovak-Americans on behalf of the Republic of Czechoslovakia.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Beneš, Edvard, 1884-1948--Correspondence.; Beneš, Edvard, 1884-1948.; Masaryk, Alice Garrigue, 1879-1966--Correspondence.; Masaryk, Jan, 1886-1948--Correspondence.; Masaryk, T. G. (Tomáš Garrigue), 1850-1937.; Tabor family.; Tabor, Edward Otto, 1885-1948.
Organizations
American Relief to Czechoslovakia.; Masaryk Institute.
Subjects
Czechs--United States.
Places
Czechoslovakia--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--Czechoslovakia.
Occupations
Lawyers.
Provenance
The papers of Edward Otto Tabor, lawyer, were given to the Library of Congress in 1956 by his children, Edward O. Tabor, Jr., John K. Tabor, and Marguerite K. Tabor Yates.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Edward Otto Tabor are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1885 Born, Oxford Junction, Iowa
1905 B.A., Tulane University, New Orleans, La.
1905 1908 Graduate work at Tulane University, New Orleans, La; taught English, history and math, New Orleans, La., high school
1908 1909 American scholar, University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wis.
1909 M.A., University of Wisconsin, Madison, Wis.
1909 1913 Taught high school English, Portland, Oreg.; worked in lumber camps in Oregon and in lead and silver mines in Idaho.
1916 LLB., Harvard Law School, Cambridge, Mass.
1917 1919 Admitted to the bar and practiced law, Pittsburgh., Pa.
1918 Present at the Czech Declaration of Independence, Philadelphia, Pa.; organized the Czech Relief Fund; did Americanization work for the Council of National Defense
1919 1923 Practiced law in partnership with W. E. Crow and S. Ray Shelby, Uniontown, Pa.
1923 1948 Practiced law, Pittsburgh, Pa.
1929 Received Order of the Revolutionary Medal from the Republic of Czechoslovakia
1929 Traveled to Europe
1932 Participated in a debate on “Revision on the Treaty of Trianon,” Williamstown, Conn.
1937 Received the Order of the White Lion from the Republic of Czechoslovakia
1937 1938 Organizer and chairman, Masaryk Institute
1927 1944 Organizer, Masaryk Birthday Dinners
1937 1938 Organizer, American relief to Czechoslovakia
1944 1948 Organizer, American relief to Czechoslovakia
1948 Died
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Edward Otto Tabor (1885-1948) consist of correspondence, reports, speeches, notes, pamphlets and clippings dealing almost exclusively with activities of Czechoslovak-Americans on behalf of the Republic of Czechoslovakia during 1918-1948. Topics include Czech news, American relief to Czechoslovakia, Thomas Masaryk’s birthday celebrations, Edvard Beneš, and the Masaryk Institute. The correspondence includes letters from Edvard Beneš, Alice Masaryk, Jan Masaryk, and other Czech officials.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged largely as received, with various material located throughout the collection. In general, however, the collection has been organized according to type or subject and therein chronologically.
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1921-1948 (Box 1)
  - Letters from Jan Masaryk, Alice Masaryk, Edvard Beneš and other prominent Czechoslovakians (Box 1)
- Material on American relief to Czechoslovakia, 1918-1948 (Box 2-3)
  - Correspondence, reports, speeches, notes, printed matter, clippings (Box 2-3)
- Material relating to Thomas G. Masaryk, 1927-1944 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, reports, speeches, notes, printed matter, clippings relating largely to the celebrations of his birthdays (Box 4)
- Material on Edvard Beneš, 1935-1947 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, reports, speeches, bills, notes, printed matter, clippings relating mostly to Beneš' visit to Pittsburgh, Pa., in 1939 (Box 5)
- Material on the Masaryk Institute, 1937-1947 (Box 6-7)
  - Correspondence, reports, speeches, printed matter, clippings (Box 6-7)
- Subject File, 1932-1945 (Box 8)
  - Correspondence, reports, printed matter, clippings relating to the Institute of Politics, Czechoslovakian Circle, Czechoslovakian Room at the University of Pennsylvania, Pittsburgh Pact, and Lidice Memorial Committee (Box 8)
- Material about Czechoslovakia, 1921-1947 (Box 9)
  - Reports, speeches, notes, printed matter, clippings (Box 9)
- Family and Personal File, 1918-1948 (Box 10)
  - Material about Domazlice, Tabor’s parents’ hometown in Bohemia; Charles Steiger, a relative; the Masons; and miscellaneous material, including correspondence, photographs, and passports (Box 10)